Have you ever just felt completely swamped?
You know, the feeling of information overload, like you're just wading through data,
wishing you could cut through it all, and well, actually get what's important.
If that sounds familiar, you are definitely in the right place.
Welcome to the Deep Dive.
Today we are diving headfirst into something truly mind-bending,
temporality and recursive dynamics.
This stuff comes from a really fascinating collection of sources we've been digging into,
collectively, called the Diatribe Repository.
And our mission today, it's unpacked this pretty radical idea.
What if time isn't just this fixed backdrop?
What if it's something that actually emerges, shaped by recursive processes?
And crucially, how understanding that changes?
Well, pretty much everything, from our own thoughts to how the universe itself might evolve.
It really is remarkable.
And what's fascinating here is how these concepts, they move beyond just abstract theory.
They actually offer practical insights into things like control, learning, even how we tell stories.
This deep dive, I think, will show how...
the Relativistic Scalar Vector Plenum, let's call it RSVP and its partner,
this recursive tiling system called Tartan,
how they give us a unified way to look at these dynamics across fields that seem, you know, totally separate on the surface.
OK, let's jump right into that central idea then.
Time, not a clock.
Yeah.
What does that actually mean?
You mentioned the Aletheos canonical form, ACF and RSVP.
How did they define this?
Right. So in ACF, one of these key repository texts,
time is explicitly defined as n.
Time is an emergent property, and crucially, it's scale dependent.
It's not just a given.
It's something that arises from the interplay of entropy, think disorder scale, and these things called causal constraints within a system.
The Dirac delta function is actually pretty central here.
It helps model locality.
Instead of time flowing smoothly everywhere, it lets the system focus dynamics at specific points.
Think of them like hotspots of information processing density.
That's where time really makes itself felt.
Wow. OK.
So time, literally,
sort of pops out of the system.
It's not just an external constant ticking away.
And how does RSVP connect with that idea?
How does it see emergent time?
RSVP, well, if we connect this to the bigger picture, it derives temporal flow, that feeling of time moving forward directly from entropic gradients and vector flux.
Imagine a river, right?
The flow isn't some external force.
It emerges from the landscape, the water's properties.
OK.
So entropic gradients are like differences in order versus disorder, and vector flux is the directed flow.
Like information moving with purpose, it's these imbalances and flows that create the progression of time, which, of course, raises a really big question.
If time emerges, what actually makes it flow in the direction we experience?
Yeah, exactly.
And this is where I think it gets really interesting.
If time emerges from these dynamics, how do recursive processes, processes that loop back on themselves, actually build structure, build meaning within that emergent time?
You mentioned universal emergence theory, UIT, and Tartan.
How do they fit in?
OK.
So UIT introduces this idea called a scalar recursion law.
Basically, distinctions or bits of information accumulate over time, and that drives expansion.
RSVP takes this idea and generalizes it, embedding recursion right into these spatio-temporal fields we talked about.
And Tartan, Tartan is the infrastructure that lets RSVP actually do this.
Think of it like a system of recursive tiles.
It breaks down scale and assigns each tile its own localized recursion, its own entropy level, even its own speed of causation.
It makes the whole theoretical recursion sort of tangible, manageable.
Got it.
So Tartan makes it concrete.
But what happens to information in these recursive systems then?
As time emerges and flows, how is information stored or changed?
That's a key point.
How is information stored?
Well, within Tartan, you can have what are called frozen tiles.
These tiles don't evolve internally.
They act like memory modules or maybe fixed anchors for meaning in a larger recursive computation.
They basically store information for recursion happening at a higher scale.
It connects beautifully, actually, to philosopher Julian Barber's idea of time capsules.
Time capsules, like snapshots of reality holding meaning outside of the flow.
That's a really powerful image.
Exactly.
But what about more abstract things like ideas or meaning itself?
How do they get frozen or maybe propagate recursively over time?
Ah, well, that leads us to another concept from the repository.
Thrisps.
They're described as self-propagating, autocatalytic, semantic, and dynamic.
Think of them as recursive instructions or ideas that actively defend themselves and try to replicate.
Like a piece of paper that says, don't throw this out or make copies of this.
That instruction turns the paper into a simple thresp.
Or like a catchy tune, maybe.
Or a meme.
Precisely.
A meme is a perfect example.
It's like a cognitive organism building these replicable patterns that get set loose in the new sphere, the realm of thought and culture.
Okay, that makes sense.
Can you give us a concrete example and maybe something historical?
what's called semantic incision and field inscription how does meaning get cut into
reality so to speak yeah there's a fascinating comparison made in the sources between bixing's
movable type printing in 11th century china and a specific retranslation of genesis 1.27
both interestingly describe a process of encoding and replicating structured meaning into some kind
of receptive medium oh so while bixing didn't just conjure characters he cut form into clay
he inscribed structure and similarly this retranslation of genesis describes
the act of creation not as making something from nothing but as cutting a pattern into
the plenum the underlying field it's a semantic act an act of imposing meaningful form not just
brute force exactly in rsvp terms you describe it as sculpting a low entropy high vector coherence
attractor a stable pattern of meaning in the semantic field guided by a specific uh
vectorial directive or intention okay this is really shifting my perspective
so if meaning and time are these dynamic fields how does this apply to say our own minds or even ai
great question in rsvp cognition itself is understood through these interacting fields
a scalar field for semantic potential the raw stuff of meaning a vector field v for referential
flow like attention and an entropy field s for ambiguity or uncertainty thinking about cognition
this way really um dramatically shifts how we understand mental states including the
world's most complex and complex and complex and complex and complex and complex and complex and
complex and complex and complex and complex and complex and complex and complex and complex and
emotions that's interesting because you know most of us think of emotions as well things like
pressure building up something you can bottle or release how does this field view explain something
so personal right that's the common metaphor like pneumatic liquids or gases but from a perceptual
control theory pct perspective which pops up in the repository emotions aren't things like that
at all there are cognitive and perceptual signals of a discrepancy discrepancy yeah the gap between
what you predict or expect and what actually happens
emotions signal shifts in your planning your executive control they're like prediction failure
alerts so anger for instance in rsvp terms that would be a disordered scalar vector dynamic a
spike in entropy maybe misaligned vector fields it reflects a breakdown in effective planning or
control and restoring function feeling better means reconfiguring those fields finding ways to lower
the entropy create more coherent plans over time restoring the flow that's yeah that's a huge shift
okay what are we going to do about this we're going to do a lot of work on this we're going to do a lot
of work on this we're going to do a lot of work on this we're going to do a lot of work on this we're going
to do a lot of work on this we're going to do a lot of work on this we're going to do a lot of work on this
something like making analogies our minds seem to do that almost instantaneously how does that fit
into a field that evolves over time ah the adapter model another piece from the repository maps
really nicely onto rsvp here it interprets analogical retrieval not as an instant lookup
but as a relaxation process in a kind of thermodynamic field like water settling
exactly like water settling your current mental state the field configuration
seeks a lower energy alignment it tries to fit itself to known attractor patterns
it tries to fit itself to known attractor patterns
familiar ways of thinking modulated by those entropy gradients
the best analogy is simply the pattern that represents a low entropy highly coherent
structural match it feels fast but it's actually a dynamic time dependent alignment process okay
and bringing this to a really pressing issue ai how does this understanding of
dynamic fields emergent time help us think about ai alignment and control that seems
like a huge challenge it is huge and forest landry another voice in the repository argued
that truly controlling super intelligent agi might even be impossible because the complexity just
scales too fast but uh there's also work like from coraggio and others on graph based control
frameworks that suggest a kind of middle ground maybe scalable oversight is possible not by
understanding every internal detail but by targeting key nodes or modulating interactions
within the ai's network like nudging the system sort of it connects to this idea of controlling
complex systems by imposing desirable global behavior like ensuring the ai follows non-deceptive
policies without needing full internal access or understanding what's fascinating here too is how
this contrasts with something like chain of thought or cod in ai which we hear a lot about for
interpretability there's this other idea chain of memory com how does that offer a different view on
ai thinking over time right com basically argues that cod often just gives us post hoc justifications
plausible stories that ai tells after the fact not the actual reasoning process true ai reasoning
deeper down in a meaningful causally structured substrate it's latent memory the language it
outputs that's often just a secondary translation layer optional even so memory first language second
exactly com reframes ai cognition as memory first language optional it emphasizes tracing the actual
causal path through the evolution of its latent memory states its vector states over time
it means the ai should ideally think before it speaks and its reasoning is structurally embedded
in the brain so it's not just you know stylistically added on afterwards so forgetting the idea of
a static blueprint for the brain rsvp suggests something much more fluid dynamic absolutely
way more fluid take cortical columns in the brain rsvp reinterprets them not as fixed processors but
as amplitwist operators amplitwist operators yeah they're local geometric operators they combine
rotation and scaling acting on neural representations so think of it your brain isn't just
shuffling files it's constantly transforming semantic spaces
concepts get bent twisted scaled by these operators as they interact and evolve over time
it gives the brain this incredible universal function approximation property
it means there's tremendous flexibility in representation all while maintaining a kind
of topological consistency neural representations become like sections of fiber bundles over the
cortical surface it's a very dynamic picture okay the implications here feel huge
if these dynamic time evolving fields apply to minds could they apply much wider
like to entire stories or even the cosmos itself well if we connect this to the bigger picture
again yes storytelling itself can be viewed through this lens of recursive entropy relaxation
each plot point each act in a story isn't just linear progression it's more like a relaxation
cycle the narrative system finds a temporary equilibrium a state of lowered entropy or tension
only for it to be destabilized again driving the story forward you could map that you could
potentially visualize it with say
dynamic entropy heat maps of a narrative spotting where a story feels like it's stagnating or maybe
getting overloaded different genres might even have characteristic entropy signatures over time
you know why certain genre blends just feel right it might be down to their entropy profiles being
compatible a story in this view becomes a kind of complete space-time structure
where the local parts contain the relationships needed to reconstruct the whole narrative as it
unfolds in its emergent time that is a truly cosmic thought
so naturally the next question the u versus evolution can we see that through this lens
of emergent time and recursion too it's definitely out there but yes the expirosis cosmological
framework another concept from the repository suggests something pretty radical it postulates
that cosmic structure didn't just arise from rapid inflation after the big bang
instead it might arise from the long time scale reintegration of decohered information
confirmation lost essentially from the cosmic microwave background the cmb reintegration
over immense time scales poincare recurrence times this entropic memory encoded somehow in scalar
and vector fields lingering from the early universe gets reabsorbed into local dynamics
the idea is that structure emerges by recapturing this lost information over vast stretches of time
through mechanisms like field coherence and semantic resonance it points to
really profound recursive temporal dynamics on a truly universal scale mind-blowing okay let's
bring it back down to earth a bit after this incredible deep dive into temporality and recursive
dynamics how does all this inform something really practical like how we learn yeah what's
fascinating here is how neatly things like self-paced mastery learning or even curriculum
design can map onto rsvp concepts you can think of learning trajectories as evolving over time
along paths that minimize entropy reducing uncertainty creating coherence in your
understanding the scalar field gradients align with these pathways so learnings is like finding
the most ordered path through information in a sense yes even something like say doing a
intensive course over a year and a half maybe that master of dialectic prose mentioned in the sources
with 365 lectures can be seen as iterative coherent sharpening it's a structured dialogue with the
material mapped perhaps to the temporal autocorrelation how correlated the state is with
itself over time of your internal semantic potential field the cuff field it highlights
learning as this continuous recursive process concepts aren't just learned once they're
constantly refined integrated sharpened over time
which naturally raises an important question how could we intentionally design learning
environments to better leverage these natural time-dependent field dynamics wow okay what an
absolutely incredible journey through temporality and recursive dynamics we've really seen how these
frameworks from the diatribe repository area rsvp tartan offer this unified language a way to
describe how time itself seems to emerge from this intricate recursive dance of information and it
applies everywhere from the tiniest cognitive processes right up to the scale of the cosmos
it really does find a lot of value in the way that we use the term time-dependent field dynamics to
knee and use as a term talking about the
associated consciousness as it is with your core спp
though it U. U.
flow of information. And if your thoughts, your ideas are like those thrisps, self-propagating
patterns you release into the world, then every decision you make, every concept you really grasp,
every story you tell, it's all actively sculpting the emergent temporal landscape of your reality
and maybe influencing the wider new sphere too. So the question to leave you with is,
what kind of temporal landscape are you creating today?